Alexander Swartz

401-626-1926 • North Kingstown, RI • alexanderswartz198@gmail.com • https://anderswartz.github.io/About-Me/

PROFILE

Dedicated student and life-long learner with a background in computer science, cognitive science, and philosophy. Accomplished speaker and presenter with exceptional communication and collaborative skills. Capable of leading projects and experienced in effectively teaching others. Motivated by curiosity and challenging problems within computer science. Currently pursuing an entry-level position related to software development.

EXPERIENCE

Computer Science Peer Tutor / Front Desk

Jan. 2021 - Present

Villanova University | Villanova, PA

After getting an A and a recommendation from the teacher, I tutor other students in courses I have already taken. In Fall 2021, I booked a Villanova-high 92% of available hours, to which my supervisor stated is "A true testament to not only your academic skills, but to your stellar ability to make students feel at home."

Chess Instructor / Summer Camp Counselor

May. 2021 - Present

Rhode Island Chess School | North Kingstown, RI

Teach and train beginner-advanced players from children to adults. Organizes and leads camp activities ranging from indoor chess tournaments to outdoor fun and games for kids ages 8-16.

Distance Education Operator

Oct. 2019 - Aug. 2020

Villanova University | Villanova, PA

Supervised and monitored AV/IT systems used for live-streaming and recording Graduate Engineering courses. Specialized in technical support for faculty, staff, and any students in the classroom.

Library Assistant / Front Circulation Desk

Jan. 2018 - Aug. 2019

Willett Free Library | Saunderstown, RI

After volunteering for 1.5 years, was given the position of library assistant (usually requires a bachelor's degree). Coordinated various community events (Kids' crafts, Summer Reading Programs, Book and Bake Sales), while managing the circulation desk.

RESEARCH

Computational Modeling of Speech Perception

Dec. 2019 - Present

Word Recognition and Processing Lab (WRAP lab) | Villanova, PA

Conducts experiments and analyzes data from the WRAP lab's neural network model of speech recognition. Specializes in the network's psychological plausibility by showing phenomena also found in human speech processing. Presented personal research at the international APCAM (Auditory Perception & Cognition Society) conference. Applies data analysis and visualization in R.

EDUCATION

Villanova University, PA

Aug. 2019 - May 2023

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science | Concentration in Cognitive Science | Minor in Philosophy

- GPA: 3.98/4.0
- Coach, Coed Intramural Softball; Volunteer, Might Writers PA; Member, Villanova Game Development Club
- Award, Margaret Cecilia Baney Writing Award Recognizing the best first-year student writing portfolios

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- High proficiency in Java. Experience in Python, R, Javascript, HTML/CSS, C, SQL (listed in order of exp.)
- Git and Github, refactoring, Test-driven development, JUnit, Maven, Continuous Integration, Jenkins, implemented RESTful APIs in Java and Javascript, Relational Database Management Systems, Software Development Lifecycle, Agile
- Strong foundation in algorithms and data structures through continually tutoring and teaching others

INDEPENDENT PROJECTS (in Java, Python, Javascript, HTML / CSS, SQL)

- NLP / AI Projects: Chess AI, Zips' Law Simulator, Wikipedia Game w/ GloVe, Sentiment Classification of Tweets
- General Software Dev. Projects: Personal Website, Rock Climbing Scoring Database, Audiometric Testing Interface